[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
so as i was saying today at the store we
have rafe kelly and rafe is a movement
educator he creates retreats called
return to the source
and he's personally inspired me to have
a deeper appreciation of the way that i
move in the natural world participate in
my environment the environment around me
that i'm living with
in hawaii i climbed up a tree
and actually fell from a tree
on an adventure with rafe and a bunch of
people and since then
uh some of the lessons like and just
like the
it seems funny to say that because it's
like yeah rafe was teaching me movement
and i fell out of a tree
but really like in that moment like
i had a really gracious fall and i felt
quite comfortably and it's actually
inspired me to take
more like risks in the way that i move
um and yeah although it was scary it was
enlivening and it showed it gave me this
um opportunity to like see how dangerous
like climbing a tree and playing like
that can be
um but it also like dialed my attention
into
another dimension of like i don't want
that to happen again
and so what that has done is when i've
been climbing a tree
like allowing myself to be very
thoughtful um in the way that i do it
and i mean ultra mindful and
so that's just one thing anytime i think
of rape i remember the time that i fell
out of a tree and i also think
that my appreciation of how that didn't
keep me from continuing to want to climb
and
and take risks with the way that i move
my body but to
do so with my attention dialed up
so anyway rafe thank you for being here
at the stoa
absolutely pleased to be here
wonderful so we titled this session um
play and meaning making
particularly because i'm very
enthusiastic about play and i'm very
interested
in how uh play and movement in the body
can inform this inform my sense making
and a lot of my sense making what i call
sense making right
has been happening like in this
container specifically like in his doom
room
with a bunch of people that are very uh
smart have great intellect um
speak eloquently um and
what i see is like their shoulders up
yeah and that's often also when i look
at myself that's what i see and like my
even
feedback of like myself is often like
what's going on from my shoulders up
so part of what was like i'm most
excited to have you here and talking
with us what i'm most curious about
is how play and movement in the body how
we can
uh bring that into this conversation and
into this practice and what we're in
what we're doing when we're doing sense
making and meeting making
so i'm curious what you any thoughts
that you have on that to kind of start
us off and then as we go anyone that has
questions please
drop them in the chat and then we'll
have an opportunity for you to ask those
so just as a note is anyone else having
trouble with tyson's feed i'm just
getting a little bit it's
lagging for me um is it just me so i'm
just trying to figure out if it's on my
end
so if you can drop a comment because i
might i might have a hard time sometimes
with questions if that's
that's a problem so um but yeah so a
couple couple things there
one was is really how do we bring the
body back
into this question back into
the culture of of
whatever it is that we're creating right
um
you know i think in some sense we're
wrestling with
uh the death of christianity um or the
resurrection of christianity depending
on your perspective but
uh the meaning making the central
organizing narrative
of the west is um
was for a long time based on
christianity and then um
that was destabilized this is you know
nichi's great uh critique of
christianity
but one thing that was interesting about
nije is that one of the things that he
really
wanted people to say uh wanted people to
do was
to sort of recover the body right the
christianity
a tradition that was very antibody
and um and to this
day i think we're still kind of stuck in
this dna where we think
of our bodies as kind of separate from
ourselves
so i'll try to come back to a
a tighter version at this point because
i think this is a really useful thing to
think about but
you talked about sense making right and
meaning making
well how do does one make sense
one actually has to move and what is
meaning
meaning is in some sense relevance to
movement
so jj gibson who is the founder of
ecological psychology he made this very
important point which is
when we perceive right sense at the most
basic
level what sense making is is being able
to make sense of the world around us and
we use our sentences to do that
but in order to use our senses we
actually have to use movement
our eyes have to be moving constantly in
order to generate
a picture of the world around us we have
to move around to try to pick up sense
we move to here
right our kinesthetic structure
receptive senses are all dependent on
movement your sense of where you are in
the world of how you inhabit your body
this is all related to movement and then
uh
many of you guys are probably inspired
by or aware of the work of jordan
peterson
and if you pick up his magnum opus
maps of meaning what he says in the
first paragraph more or less
is that we can look at the world in two
ways
one is as a world of objects and the
other is as
a forum for action action
meaning movement right and
the second way of viewing the world is
the view of the world that came from
traditional religion that came from
additional sense making structures
that is embedded in literature that is
embedded in storytelling that's embedded
in flow
and um and that's the world of meaning
right and what is the meaning
that they're talking about well the
meaning is relevance to action
so peterson was of course one of the
biggest influencers to many of us in the
world of thinking about sense making
in the beginning of his book he's saying
that what
makes something make sense what makes
something have meaning
is its ability to guide you into being
able to act
and unfortunately as a culture we have
neglected
a huge percentage of the self
that is relevant to that so
thus big zarathustra nietzsche talks
about the intellectual
as um a shriveled atrophied man with a
giant
ear right and if we think about john
verveigh who many of you guys in here
are big fans of as well
talks about this four ways of knowing
propositional
um procedural uh perspectival and
participatory
right everyone's aware of these
hopefully in this chat
um so
when you sit down and you consume
wikipedia articles or you watch youtube
videos or you listen to podcasts
what we're doing right now is
propositional
right and what we're doing is we are
we are feeding this part of ourselves
the part of us that
absorbs and becomes better at juggling
semantic propositions
but your ability to actually achieve
anything in the world
is always you know more than that
we have to have procedure right so
um you have to actually be able to act
something out you have to be able to do
it i can tell you how to do a movement
i can give you
all the words but it doesn't mean you
can do the mood and doesn't mean that
you understand what the world looks like
and understanding how to apply that
movement
it doesn't mean that you understand how
that that that movement has shifted your
role in your relationship with the world
so we need movement so
so yeah so that's a that's a good a good
place to start
yeah it's really good i've been doing a
weekly session here called flowing with
unknowingness where we practice
freestyle
and do dialogue have a conversation
with beats playing and there's something
about the freestyle that
catalyzes for me like moving my hands
and my arms and
bringing in this like rhythmic movement
while i'm speaking
and even just noticing how that
influences the space
and like the capacity of the group to
create a story together
and sort of let that that that dialect
or
i don't want to call it but let the
dialogue kind of guide the conversation
there's something about the movement
that is very helpful
to allowing uh what we might call like
emergence or presencing
so i think what i'm interested in is how
when we're doing dialogue we're doing
storytelling
how does uh and in your experiences
because you really bring
like the dialogue practices and
storytelling together with movement
for groups of people out in the
wilderness
so i'm interested in how our movement
um informs our capacity to like do
dialogue and allow what some call like
regenerative emergent presencing
type of conversation this generative
conversation
and how might we continue to practice
bringing more of that movement and that
rhythm into
dialogues like this yeah
first thing that occurs to me when
you're talking about that is uh
i'm curious everyone in the chat if you
were uh
also at the embodied movement summit
that we just put on drop a little
check mark in the chat i'm curious how
many of you guys were there but my
friend simon thacker
did a really wonderful presentation on
the role of dance and gesture
uh in the origin of communication right
so his theory is that the human ability
to mimic
and create expressive movement actually
preceded
our ability to have articulated language
and that we have this incredibility to
express empathy for other animals and we
know that
when we're more passionate when we're
more articulate we use our hands more we
use our gestures more so the the part of
you that generates
uh speech which is very closely related
to the part of you that can generate
articulated thought
um is is motorically linked to your
ability to gesture
and so we might then think that fluidity
in those things is somewhat interrelated
so here's a uh one way in which we can
think that this is a way of better
integrating the self
one of my big sort of passions is this
idea that
that a lot of things that are often seen
as in opposition to each other
are actually meant to be integrated it's
not that doesn't mean it's easy to
integrate them
um but we grow through integration right
we need to be able to uh
we need to be able to express
masculinity we need to be able to
express femininity right and there's
immature femininity and immature
masculinity and then there's an
integrated
appropriately balanced for you as an
individual mature expression of those
things
right right you have to be able to be
assertive and you also have to be able
to be
compassionate and in the same way
the mind and the body have to be
expressed and they have to be better
integrated
so when we have our events we go out and
we run and jump and climb in a rough
house and we experience intense
physicality and we experience
fear and we experience joy and
experience pleasure
physically and then we talk about it
right we insight generate off of it and
we ask people to tell stories
so for instance this year we asked
everyone to
to tell a story of their day as an
individual
right so one day we went and had a crazy
epic adventure
and then um we asked people okay
what would this story sound like if it
was still remembered a thousand years
from now
right it had been turned into this epic
adventure that was meaningful for people
a thousand years from now
how would you tell that story right how
would it have been um
i've been shifted and uh and then the
next night we had them
join in little tribes and did the same
exercise
so what we could
is engaging in sense making as you said
engaging in building our capacity for
articulation
but we're intentionally linking physical
action
we're intentionally linking physical
culture into the rest of our culture
we talk about this um this balance
between
four pillars of self-development i'm not
claiming that these pillars are
exhaustive
but i think they're very a very good
start and those are
you you need a movement practice you
need a mindfulness practice
you need a um a nature connection
practice and you need community
practices
if you have those things uh you're going
to be
doing pretty well so
we notice is that each of these things
grounds and
affords greater transformation through
each other so for instance
many people struggle when starting a
meditation practice
um sitting down and concentrating on
your breath
can be very very difficult to do
however i believe that if you have that
same person
doing parkour or martial arts
and you point out to them their ability
to stay in flow
and focused and not be distracted
in while they're participating in the
sport
it will ground and make they will see
the benefits of the meditation
much earlier and they will in fact get
the medi uh the benefits faster because
they're going to be
doing two things that teach you how to
access the flow state at the same time
so you i know that when i don't
concentrate i
fall or when i don't
have a way of typically training
concentration all of a sudden these two
things are relevant to each other
and then they're mutually
inter-affording and causing
transformation
and then we can look at something like
um time in nature same thing
right i have a nature meditation
practice of sitting and listening to
tune out everything else in my life and
be able to actually
listen to the birds is dependent on my
ability to have good concentration
but those birds are way more interesting
and informational right and they add so
much richness
and then of course when i have a
movement
to practice all these things become the
place where i can have real dialogue and
real stories
with um with the people
um in my life right so how many
conversations have you had about the
weather
those can be very very meaningless
but actually they can be very very
meaningful when you're a surfer
or a canyoneer right how many
conversations have
you had about the latest tv show the
latest
you know how much more meaningful is it
in your life when you're talking about
i did this crazy jump i had this amazing
sparring session
versus these things happened on a game
of thrones
right um so so we think that
that that in this in this
uh we actually think the movement is
primary
right that it's the first place that we
should go the play is the first place
that we should go
because fundamentally cognition and
everything else about us and
language right our ability to speak this
dialogue we're doing right now it is
movement
pulling out moving patterns in our head
we don't have a good relationship with
ourselves and our body
um i think we're
in our in our bodies embeddedness in the
environment
i think it really weakens our ability to
pursue any of these other things that
we're looking to pursue
there's actually one of my students
robert lansdale who pointed out
something i really liked
uh jordan peterson who mentioned before
famously says
if you would change the world you know
first clean your own room
and he said but there's actually
something closer to you than your room
right it's your body right do you have
your
relationship to your own body and its
capacity to move and
express itself and connect to the world
around it
is that an order and if that's
disordered
if you're deeply uncomfortable insecure
fearful
in your body are you really going to be
able to
go out and effectively change the world
in a powerful way
so hopefully that was helpful tyson i
got a little rant there but
um let me know what's where do you want
to go from there
as yeah great um as you guys have
questions please drop them in the chat
i'm gonna ask another
question i'm gonna go and then i'm gonna
go to a question i got via email
so i my curiosity now is like
guiding principles for developing a
movement practice
um it's i think it's an interesting
opportunity right now because
gyms closed people not
and be available so what are some
guiding principles for developing a good
movement practice that will
um work in synergy with that ecology of
practices
yeah absolutely so i actually i think i
want to do
a little exercise right let's let's get
a little bit more
embodied here so
the breath is always something very
powerful to go back to
and even if you're you know in solitary
confinement you can play with
so we're here we're in a very
cognitive space let's tune into our body
for a second
notice if you're breathing into your
belly
into your chest up into your clavicles
notice if the sides of your top belly
are expanding
notice if the back of your body is
is there tension anywhere that you're
holding with the breath
when we you know we live very
cognitively stressful
lives
at any time that we want to go into the
body and be with the body
a very basic starting place can be how
is my breath
so i personally notice a feeling of
tension in my chest right now
um got a lot of work stress at the
moment and i think that's what it's
expressing
so i'll kind of ask my body you know is
there tension here that i can release
that i don't need
and can i return to a breath that
involves the belly the chest
all the way up a little bit
with a pause both at the top of the
inhale
and most importantly
at the bottom of the exhale
you're always switching between a
sympathetic state
right fight flight fight or freeze
um
or a parasympathetic state rest
digest breed you know
and even the breast cycle has this
yin and yang aspect to it breathing in
is yang
breathing out is yin it's
parasympathetic
and that the pause at the bottom
of our exhale is actually the most
parasympathetic place
so when we can extend our exhale
and extend that time without stress not
forcing it but just allowing there to be
a longer pause
it teaches our body to settle into our
parasympathetic
so now if there's anywhere outside that
you can take a look
and just observe nature
for me my movement practice the origins
of my
practice come from nature i was a kid
who grew up at the end of a dirt road
that's been in my family since
the 1920s since 1920 it was homesteaded
and i spent many many years walking
through the woods and then
jumping and climbing and roughhousing
with my friends and
some ways i'm just doing more
sophisticated versions of that now
and i find that whenever my practice
becomes oppressive or you know i'm
tyrannical with myself or i'm
overstressed my body isn't feeling good
um and i need some way to reset that
simply
walking in the woods is the best way to
do that so we're not going to get up and
take a walk but we can
imagine what it would be like if we just
stepped outside our door
and here in washington right now the
sun's shining
it's a beautiful day it's blue sky
birds how would it be to settle in and
walk through
those woods to be in that nature
and as i'm walking you know when you
first start walking in the woods maybe
you just walk
but you might find a fallen log and want
to
climb across it you might see a low
laying
uh hanging limb and what to hang from it
every child has this inherent capacity
and they'll explore their environment
and all of us still have that inside
ourselves we just have to learn to let
go of the social conditioning that says
that it's not okay
we have to see the world as
a forum for action
that we're not constrained from so
you know we have whole programs we have
lots of ways of building up the skills
there's
millions of free tutorials on on uh on
any physical skill you want on youtube
there's a lot of stuff out there but for
me fundamentally um
go outside
horse time breathe be with nature
that's how you get started
perfect thank you i would love
to get to some of the questions um and
then we got some more moving in now
danny you sent me a question i would
love for you to
unmute yourself and ask it if you'd like
yeah by memory uh i just came across
someone
i don't know if you're familiar with
gurjeev you know he's the spiritual
mystic from the 30s 20s you know
anyway he's this phrase
that he said was that we our
consciousness our spirit
needs us to feed our senses
and and his how he
how he uh he took that was that we
needed to
get ourselves in new environments so
that
it sparked it but it seems like your
work
is about seeing what's here
just in a new way that that's going to
feed our senses
you know it's going to change our
perspective and all the i just like that
phrase feed
the senses and and that we forget
to do that really or we use um
you know television to do that
yeah oh man that that reminds me of um
khalil gabron the prophet you know
exactly the earth longs to uh
uh to feel your feet upon it uh to
caress it right
the wind longs to caress you um
there's another wonderful book so
clogabron the prophet is a really
wonderful book another one is called the
spell of descentus
by david abrams but it's basically about
the idea that
that that fundamentally we are supposed
to be phenomenologically exp
us through our senses and that we have
become blind
to the senses in some sense and we've
become illiterate
um i had this image the other day that
that that uh that a modern westerner
walking through nature
is like someone who couldn't read
walking to the library of alexandria
right there's so much signal and you're
completely blind to it
um in
in raviki has introduced me to 4e
cognitive science right
we have um embodiment right
and now embodiment is this big word
that's becoming
a major sort of organizing principle
around how we can do sense making how we
can grow and how can gain meaning in our
lives
but there's also embeddedness right so a
cognitive agent
has to essentially be in something that
has
motor capacity in order to form
its cognition cognition is bootstrapped
off of motor capacity
but it's not just that you have a body
it's the body
only exists in relationship to an
environment it's embedded in the
environment
right and then cognition is enacted you
have to actually
act things out in order to organize and
grow
and then you have to um and then it's
extended right that's the community
aspect we have to be connected into
a network of other people so the way
that i
um you know this is a very old debate
right in philosophy goes back to plato
and before plato but i really like
the not the platon platonic viewpoint
but the other viewpoint which is that
the world is always changing right um i
can't remember who it was famous foster
was kind of a
you know he was opposed to to plato's
ideal ideal performance but he said
a man never steps in the same river
twice because the river is always
changing and so is the man
or woman um and we
right like i walk by a tree and i think
oh that tree looks kind of interesting
um and then maybe maybe
i don't know what kind of tree it is and
then maybe i learned some other trees
and i realized oh that's a that's a
portuguese laurel tree
and i and i play in it and i see certain
things in it and then i exhaust those
things and i don't see it
and then years later i come back to the
same trees and i say
oh wow now there's a bunch of new things
here and it
slowly reveals itself to me and new
layers of meaning are possible
and that's through the parkour practice
but also like
i could learn about the value of the
wood in that tree and how it's used and
how it
reacts to fire or how it is used in
carpentry
or i can know what kind of birds feed on
the
berries of that tree or whether they're
edible for human beings
or what what season the tree flowers in
what animals are attracted to those
flowers what insects
so there's this um
there's an inexhaustibleness to the
natural world where you can observe the
same
area over and over again and always be
coming back to a new country
always be revealing new vistas to
yourself
and this is
uh very closely connected to this is
essentially what what verveiki describes
as the sacred those things that are
inexhaustibly revealing themselves to
you that you can always learn from
i think of um the trees that i try to
i always have a new lesson for me every
time that i come back
so um yeah that's that's that's
that's how it being and that's the
sacred
i mean that's when you're making that
link that's gorgeous
that's how i view the sacred english
lovely
thank you thanks danny
peter will you ask your question
how's it going ralph here nice to meet
you
yeah nice to meet you man welcome to the
stoa uh it's good to have you here
so my question was i know you're uh
peterson
and vaki have been an influence on you
um and they're like
top-heavy a lot of propositional heavy
uh
content that they're throwing out there
and i wonder how that's
shaped and informed your understanding
of your own
embodied movement practices and maybe
how you
um went about them differently
yeah that's a big question um i could do
like a long very long presentation on
the influence of those two thinkers so
i'm going to try to to see how short
they can make it
i i guess
one way to think about it is that
physical cultures have an inherent
meaning system
that may not be explicitly
prescribed right or explicitly explained
right
i actually think that a lot i think
there's some very deep cultural dna for
instance
in a lot of our physical culture that
comes out of
the period of romanticism and
nationalism because
gymnastics for instance was formed
around the same time as like
pan-aryan german nationalism
by people who were deeply involved in it
right gymnastics our way germany was
like the original founding of that
and um rugby soccer tennis
cricket all these games were codified
uh during the period the height of the
british empire
and you know later they said that the
battle the the battle of water
field was one upon the fields of eden
right which is
the famous british boarding school the
idea being that the
the culture of these young soldiers have
been formed by these games that have
been created
and so there's all these interesting
things that come out of that and i
i i think that parkour was a kind of
emergent culture
that came out of this
basically a very deeply traumatized
group of
immigrant kids right uh parkour is
formed in the
ghettos of paris the bandlers of paris
um by kids who are a lot of them are via
are mixed vietnamese
their families can escape vietnam during
the the franco-vietnamese war
um some of them uh one of them was from
new caledonia other ones are from west
africa
and these kids
they they basically were you know the
type of kids who might have ended up in
gangs they were struggling in school
and they wanted to test themselves and
see how they can become strong human
beings
and so they test themselves with with
you know how many push-ups can we do how
many pistol squats can we do
how many you know how far can we jump
all these things
um and and then that
those movements some of the movements
that they did were picked up and
spread across the world through youtube
and so we kind of got
only a small piece of it and then we
were trying to replicate it
and it was very meaningful for me in the
beginning but
eventually it was like there were i
couldn't figure out some of the pieces
and i started to sort of pull in uh
culture
sense making from like the team the
elite sports world right
from track and field gymnastics and so i
got very into like
being very goal oriented and having very
clear progressions and creating
competitions
and there are some aspects of that that
were great but ultimately
it didn't take me where i needed to go
and i got injured a lot and i was
it was it was a kind of a game that that
was self-extinguishing
so then i got really interested in play
and play was very powerful
and it took me a very good direction i i
exploded in
a lot of ways
i was in nature all the time and i
really enjoyed it but there was a point
at which i could
feel that i was sort of becoming too
disorganized there wasn't enough
structure there was enough clarity about
where i was going
and i was starting to articulate this
idea that i wanted
that there was something bigger than
just being the best athlete and from a
technical perspective or winning a
competition
that we had to be oriented towards and i
i wrote a piece called the self-worth
assuming which was about my
this idea that that it's no good to to
try to
to just love yourself as you are you
actually have to start
cultivating the self in a way that you
will admire
into the future and i also had noticed
at that time that
the people were very interested in the
stories that i was telling you most
rather than the kind of statistical
scientific knowledge that i had
and i was trying to understand the value
of narrative and story
and that's
and i listened to the the political
aspect of that and it was interesting
but as soon as he got into the
archetypal stuff i was
really hooked so i went and watched the
whole maps of meeting series from 2017
uh the whole um personality series
and then i was kind of confused though
because i i didn't
know exactly why i was paying so much
attention to this when it didn't seem to
be really deeply related to the work
that i was doing
because before that i was spending lots
of time on gymnastics and strength
conditioning and
track and field podcasts and then i went
to teach
a workshop it was my first workshop of
the year because i
spent about four months off the road
between you know the fall and the spring
and i started telling my stories and my
anecdotes about evolution
and how that was related to how we
became better human movers
and all of a sudden this petersonian
perspective would
sort of assert itself and i would say oh
wow boom
this is the same thing same thing same
thing and then i sort of had this this
realization that his
project of you know helping people
recognize how to create the most heroic
version of themselves in a way
was essentially what i've been doing at
just a different level i've been doing
it with the body
and then i ran into verveiki's work
and viveki just gave me so much
deeper insight into that and different
ways of looking at that
right looking at his self-transcendence
versus the creation of the heroic self
you know singing about the four e's the
four p's of knowledge
um i sometimes think i i told raviki
this that like
jaw that um jordan's work like built so
much cognitive
architecture in my brain that it was
kind of hard to
to get to to move it around um
and so it was like he he created more of
the base for me to interact with john's
work with
but now i kind of think of like jordan's
work is like being
work is more like an ether that's
sifting through everything
and shifting it feels like go is
happening in my brain
um if that makes sense so i don't know
if that is a
completely coherent story um but
i've found even though both those guys
are heady
it's kind of interesting because jordan
talks a lot about rough and tumble play
that was one place
that we really that i really was
interested in
that's one of the conversations that i
really like to have with him and in his
own story
you know when he sort of made himself
right he got into strength training
right and he has a chapter in his book
called don't bother
children when they're skateboarding so
when i met jordan we talked about
parkour
um and you know he was super into it
he's super excited about what was
happening in the parkour world
uh and then with john you know he's a
taishi schwann
practitioner right he wants to come to
return to the source
um and and you know he's just
sort of like as soon as we've had a
conversation he's been incredibly
passionate about sort of forwarding what
i'm talking about into this world
because
because he sees it as a big missing
piece
cool that was awesome thank you
megan will you ask your question about
education
um thanks for all the thoughts so far um
this has been really interesting um
i'm a i'm a music teacher um i started
with one child at once
um teaching them the violin and asking
them to stand up straight and put their
feet on the ground and
play the violin and focus for 20 minutes
and then i worked into teaching in quite
big groups
um mostly um five to ten year olds
and i've been getting more and more
interested in what's going on in
mainstream education as well
um and so personally i'm trying to
really break out of the idea
where we um ask the kids to to switch
off
from the rest of their bodies and so in
the case of violin you know it's
fingertips um fingertips only
and arms and ignore ignore the rest of
the body i'm
personally i'm trying to break out of
that idea um so i'm really interested in
what's going on in mainstream education
which is often seeing the idea that kids
need to move their bodies as a kind of
obstacle that we need to overcome
um and for example there are um there
are these web services
um that produce short movement videos
designed to splice in between your maths
lesson and your english lesson
in class to get all the kids um you know
standing up and wiggling around for five
minutes and then they can sit down and
put their heads down and do their math
um which seems like a i mean it's a very
it's very separatist uh way of solving
that problem is you know splicing this
little five minutes of movement in
between the
um in between the um the cognitive um
tasks um that cut off the body
completely
so um i'm wondering if you can if you
know of any um any positive
um movements going on in children's
education um any people who are doing
some interesting work with integrating
those things together
um that you could uh point us to or
speak on
um i have a few thoughts there so
the first first thing that pops into my
brain is um
my friend kelly starrett who had runs
the ready state
a pretty big name in the um strength
condition world he and his wife
have a program called uh stand-up kids
and it is a basically they're replacing
sit-down desks with stand-up desks but
they
have a kind of special feature which is
that they have a bar on the bottom of
them
that the kids can put their feet on that
wiggles so it's basically
a a wiggle channeling device let's call
it um but they found that when they did
this
kids
[Music]
way more cows they were here they're
more more engaged in school um
you know many people have observed that
walking actually helps us
so if we need to think about something
difficult going on a walk
can be a very good thing so in the same
sense um
you might find that creating these
stand-up desks that have this capacity
to wiggle
actually helps kids learn better um
did you guys all get that i kind of i
know my my internet just went unstable
it said
give me a thumbs up yeah we got that
cool and then
so the next thing i would that that
occurs to me that's interesting is
i mean in a sense music education
is physical
it is a movement right you are learning
to control its motor control versus say
gross motor control like i might be more
focused on
um but the same type of principles apply
so i will be looking for
thinkers who are applying ecological
dynamics and constraintly approach
learning and um external cue learning
to uh uh the movement space i think
that'll be very interesting
i know that i've run into a few things
where we're learning
music is very close related to the type
of things that that we're finding are
are effective in um in in
in learning right so a lot of
traditional movement practices part
practice where you're you're
you're you're breaking things down to
very small pieces and trying to build
them up
um and we are we've done the same thing
in
in physical pedagogy and in both
it appears that generally learning is
optimized when you actually try to take
on bigger chunks
and then there's a whole uh a whole
breakdown of that
basically having to do with optimizing
cognitive difficulty
and so the level of of challenge that
you want
is variable you have to look at the
teaching effect versus the
um the session effect so
really interesting finding from motor
learning theory is that
there's a pretty strong disjunction
between what's called the session
result which is how much someone
improves in a session
and the teaching result which is how
much that improvement is retained from
session to session
so very often what's called blocked
practice like you practice
this scale than the scale than this
scale outperforms
in session uh result but underperforms
in um like long-term result compared to
actually playing the whole song and just
playing the whole song repeatedly even
though you make errors
um so i hope those are interesting
thoughts but
but yeah stand-up kids is great for
general stuff and then
i i agree with you that that having kids
just
move and then just do cognition is not
the best way to do it that if we can
integrate these two things if we can
have them say play soccer and then
explore
how what soccer informs them about
geometry um
that we're going to get a better result
right a lot of this learning that i've
done around statistics and math has been
about
just trying to understand all the
physical stuff that i want to do
lots of snowboarders skateboarders have
gotten really good at
uh geometry and because you know
that's how they figure out how to make
these giant jumps and how to jump on
them and not die
so i think there's a lot of kids who
would who would improve much faster if
we could leverage some of these things
hopefully that was helpful
mark would love to have you ask your
question
sure so um
i was wondering if you noticed anything
with uh shifts in perspective from
people who go through your
course and what kind of shifts they
might have as a result of
uh spending time in the woods with you
that are
um that's there's lots of shifts in
perspective right um
so
so very often people when they look at
physical practices experience a lot of
fear and trepidation going into the
practice
and they find through the practice that
they're more capable
than they realized they're more robust
than they realized
and their sense of empowerment and
overcoming fear and their relationship
to fear changes dramatically
also obviously their relationship to
nature changes they see nature
differently
they see the natural world differently
and then with our longer retreats
there's a massive shift for people in
how they
how they perceive relationships and what
is possible for them
in relationships and how they can
communicate with other people
how they want to be communicated with
how much
intimacy they're actually missing in
their lives
and how much
that sense of intimacy of the sense of
being meaningful to other people
a sense of having experiences that are
deeply meaningful
that are part of a group
i don't know that i can i feel like
there are so many changes of perspective
that would be really difficult
to to articulate them all but
i guess one way to think about it
is we talk about this idea there's
reconnections right the people are
disconnected and
alienated as a kind of default state in
the modern western world
and they're disconnected and alienated
from knowing what
who they are and what they want and what
is meaningful to them
because we have a kind of educational
system that's focused
on extrinsic rewards followed by a
professional world that's largely driven
by perfect
extrinsic rewards and without access to
play it can become very easy to
be unaware of what is interesting
know what you like you don't know what
actually motivates you then you just
don't know who you are um so we
reconnect with the self obviously
we move from a kind of very cognitive
oriented
style of engaging with the world towards
a more body-oriented style of engaging
with the world so
we shift perspective from mental to
physical in a way
we change our story around play in the
meaning of play
and that's very powerful and we change
our story and our
our perspective around nature and then
obviously as i said on community
and uh what we find is that people
find those transformations incredibly
meaningful and powerful
so we're really motivated to try to get
more people to experience them
awesome personally in one of my
experiences with rafe he had us
he guided a group of us through moving
with each other
by actually like grabbing um each
other's heads
there's a specific specific way to
safely grab onto someone's head and
actually guide them
around and move their body and it was
amazing for me to realize
uh well one thing the level of surrender
that i could feel in the hands of
another person
that i wasn't expecting like i thought
it would be tense and rigid and scared
and so one shift for me was realizing
like how
uh relaxing it was to be like
dragged around by my head um in a way
and then the other was to realize that
house to do that and we had others we
would grab
um at their arm or different things but
to realize how
foreign another person's body felt to me
and this how i did i i had a
i didn't like that like it was like it
revealed something to me where i was
like oh
there's a lot of opportunity for me here
like another person's body feels like
um off limits to touch
which there are reasons for that and
consent and all that is
very important um but to to to realize
how interesting a body is and how i want
to be able to move with another body
um that was i mean that's that's
definitely something that stuck with me
and like i had created a curiosity
that's led me
to yeah like to
connect with people in a way that maybe
my my words and my language in the past
has fallen short
yeah and how that intimacy in my life
typically has been saved for a very
um small group of people and but there
is something that
opens up with the person and the way we
can communicate and understand each
other and team up
when there are other pathways for
intimacy
yeah so i fell inspired to share that
and i would love to hear um robert
asks question
sorry i said in the dark i didn't want
to seem too creepy when i turned
everything on
um so my question i'll just read it the
body is kind of universal and and can
transcend everything and be a frame big
enough
for kind of all of us on the planet so
um do you have any insights or anecdotes
into how like your philosophy can create
a common ground
or like surprising relationships and
surprising could be like
negative or anything it doesn't mean
good necessarily
yeah the first thing occurs to me is
actually that
um like i would describe myself as a
pretty hyper masculine
individual without a lot of connection
to the feminine
uh necessarily and i can find um
female minds to be um
and through teaching and sharing these
things i've had lots of really wonderful
opportunities
to um to be able to see the world from
a woman's perspective and to draw value
from that
and to grow from it so i feel like it's
easier for me to teach
you know kind of the easiest population
for me to teach is like
15 to 22 year old per athletic males
right
they just kind of see the same way that
i do you know
we'll be loud and abrasive and push each
other around a lot in domineering and
it's great but
i learn a lot more when i work with
female students
and i really enjoy that so
i'll tell you guys a little story about
that when i first started teaching
parkour
we were doing a lot of really intense
conditioning as part of our training so
for instance we do we'd say okay we're
only going to do
10 push-ups but every push-up would take
like 60 seconds and we'd be in like 30
different positions
then almost everyone would fail by the
time that we got through these 10
push-ups
then we do the same thing for squats and
then we'd go for a run
pretty much every female student that
i'd had in the class had cried
one another and a number of years um so
i was pretty alarmed
by this and i would
kind of become obviously alarmed by it
apparently during class and would sort
of give too much attention to
the person who was crying which
generally only made it worse
and so i had one of our one of our
apprentices who was a woman come to me
and say
like you may not have cried in several
years but
um these women you're you're responding
to
probably cry pretty regularly so you
just need to relax and not make such a
big deal out of it
and so i did and sure enough like they
pretty much just stopped crying in most
of my classes and
the problem resolved itself now a few
years later i was at
return of the source our big event and
um
one of our students had was up ahead of
me on the creek we were
running down wacom creek and she'd come
up to a jump between two boulders
over a waterfall and one of uh one of
the other students who is also a coach
was telling her that she could do it
right you can do this absolutely you can
do this you know he's encouraging her to
get ready for this jump
and i i saw that she was physically
capable of doing the job
um but i ran up and sort of i didn't
want her to feel too pressured right i
didn't want her to feel like she had to
do the jump in order to be accepted as
part of the group
so i said like i know that you can do
this jump and i'm here to support you if
you want to do this jump but you don't
have to do the job
it's your choice and she asked me is it
okay if i cry while i do the jump
and i said yeah absolutely
jump jump right like whatever is your
own process your own way of doing it
you do that um and so she did the jump
and she was crying when she landed on
the other side she was still crying and
she was laughing and she was crying and
we walked away and we talked about how
that was good and that was powerful and
it was wonderful and it was great
and so that's become a big story about
what we learned from these things
now the story continues because
maura now has come back to return to the
source more often than any other student
she's been there for five years in a row
and she kind of cringes when i tell this
story
because she doesn't cry anymore and she
does pretty crazy things
right last year she jumped to this year
she jumped off a 30 cliff for the first
time
last year she did a back flip off of a
rope swing for the first time
um but without
the education that janine gave me i
wouldn't have been ready in the moment
for maura
and so uh
that was a connection and awareness that
has been really powerful
and i've also seen um i've seen
lots of beautiful moments like that we
year before last or 2019
we had
you know sometimes conversations around
gender sexuality
violence uh can come up around the rough
and tumble play that we do
that can be very can be a very revealing
place for people
and people people had that come up and
we had some folks in the group who were
who were um who were women who were
traumatized and had a
history of trauma and had adopted a very
strong kind of anti-patriarchy
uh belief system um but it turned out we
also had men in
the group who had been abused by
ex-girlfriends and men who'd been raped
by women
and that came out in the process of
yeah and it was really
powerful because there were women in the
group who
didn't know beforehand that such a thing
could happen to a man or didn't have a
felt sense that that was possible
and didn't really have any empathy for
that idea and a man but when they saw
these very strong
very capable men um talk about this
experience it changed things for them
and at the same time for those men
to be witnessed by women who they might
have thought of as their ideological
enemies
in their vulnerability and not to be um
attacked for it and not to be looked
down on for it
oh it was incredibly powerful in healing
so that's a
that's my best answer to that question
thank you well that brings us through a
full hour we do have a couple questions
in here rafe do you have
time for a question or two more or must
we let you go
yeah i'm happy i'm happy to answer some
more questions wonderful well monique i
would love to have you ask your question
you have to unmute yourself monique
ah okay hi hi thanks everything you
shared so far
um i was wondering because of the whole
embodied the need for
more embodied work in usual sessions of
co-working or collaboration or
thinking together in groups but now
we're in this long lockdown
and we've got the places like the store
and many other places where we're mostly
stuck behind screens and will be for a
while and whether you have thoughts
about
that the the kind of embodied culture we
need to start
or tactics we need to start introducing
in our sessions
these long-term virtual sessions that we
probably will be in
yeah i was introduced to this idea
recently of strong versus weak
connection um and i think it's a really
powerful way
to think about the information ecologies
that we're experiencing right like how
much bandwidth how much information
am i receiving from you as i'm looking
at you on the screen
and so one thing that i uh
that i've noticed personally is that
like text
twitter facebook they're you know
you can do a lot of commun
it's very hard to get good communication
to happen um
so i i think that this is a wonderful
thing because essentially
like we are taking social media and
we're making it
much more real in a way um
now i've noticed an interesting thing
which is that people know me from my
movement work
and they often ask me to come on and do
some kind of movement thing
on a call like this and i always find
that really uncomfortable because my
movement work involves being out there
in nature right
so it's like everybody pull up their
tree
and let's all swing around on it doesn't
work so well
or everybody start wrestling with your
your partner
doesn't work so well on this type of
frame but i do like this
um but i i think as i was
as i was talking today i had the sense
of like oh we need to do something right
and i think just breathing was a really
good place to start right
like sitting here and all trying to
breathe together
right that's another level of physical
connection right there's a physical
intimacy that comes through that and
obviously we could do basic physical
exercises together and we could play
with rhythm together
or um you know as tyson might have you
guys do you're
there's a beat we're all experiencing
the same beat and we're all responding
to the same beat we're all moving to the
same beat
and all these things can increase our
kinesthetic empathy for each other
so those are some ideas i think that
would be useful as a
game involved with them that involve
movement that connect us
thank you you're welcome
excellent we have a peter a question
from connor also
hey ray um
good to see you so i was wondering what
would you think of that potential for
uh mentality especially if it's
outdoors or shared with other people as
it gets better for
combining like the aspirational and
imaginative qualities of video games
along with their capacity for inducing
flow states with
an appreciation for nature and athletics
especially something like pokemon go if
it got better for
affording like a new kind of animism
that helps people
care more about the ecology as well
yeah um
it's an interesting question does that
return the source with us
so um nice to see you connor um
i know that you're a pretty big video
game player
what it sounds like and a lot of people
who follow me are and love video games
and i
tend to have a pretty negative
relationship to video games personally
um
so to back up so
there's a video that i recorded a few
years ago that
has me climbing through a waterfall
right and it's the same waterfall that
we climbed through at return to source
and when i showed that video to my dad
my dad said wow rafe must've been real
scary climbing up through that waterfall
we only ever climbed down you know
so this waterfall is 45 minutes away
from my dad where my dad grew up in a
different town
buried in the very hard to access area
of this park and somehow as a kid he'd
found it
and climbed it and that was an
expression of the type of
thing that my dad did as a kid right he
they built 70-foot rope swings
my dad learned how to do backhand
springs and front handsprings
um in pe class and
he uh when he was like 46 or seven years
old he built a a diving board on our
property into a new pond that he'd built
and i was hanging out with him at the
time and he started bouncing on the
diving board and he went up and he did
a front flip into a dive
and i'd never seen him do a flip in my
entire life and he just pulled it out
and it was beautiful and perfect first
time he did it
and you know when i started doing
parkour
you know we i started hearing all these
stories from people who had
been kids with my dad about the way that
he used to run and jump and climb
through the woods and
slide out of cedar trees and that's kind
of how i grew up
up to a point but when i was about 10
all my friends started playing video
games
and they stopped running around in the
woods with me they stopped being
physically active
and i think that by and large video
games have been
incredibly powerful in moving people
away
from physical activity so a number of
years ago my friend stefan guiana said
to me um
has done is they've divorced flavor from
nutrition
right so you can get sweetness now
without all the fiber
water and phytochemicals and fruit you
can get
you know um you can get bright colors
and get all this stuff
you make hyper stimulating products with
very little
nourishment in them and as soon as he
said that i thought to myself oh like
well this is just how you win at
capitalism late stage capitalism because
uh pornography is sexuality divorced
from
relationships where all the learning
happens right and video games
burst from any physical capacity
so kids spend their time accessing their
flow states
exercising just their thumbs and i don't
think that it's very powerful
in uh the development of a human being
generally now a lot of kids have found
parkour through
through you know mirror's edge or
assassin's creed
um but the amount of kids who would have
been doing
parkour naturally not knowing what it
was
um before parkour is much higher in my
opinion the amount of kids who
found parkour just through one of these
things so i'm very negative about video
games in general
i didn't like them as a kid very much
and i was pretty
upset when i couldn't get my friends to
go run around in the woods again
anymore with me when i when i reached a
stage where everyone found games and i
felt like and i actually believed that
my progression as an athlete was
[ __ ] by that
because i didn't have anyone to push me
and to do things and to
like go through adolescence running and
jumping and climbing
um
so anyways that's my background on it so
i haven't thought a lot about that
generally when i think about the future
and augmented reality and vr and all
those things i just think
run as fast as you can away from this
right i think the future like uh you
know
technology peaked in the 90s for me as
far as
affording human happiness and everything
that we've done since has been a mistake
so uh i may not be the most unbiased
person thinking about this
and and you probably disagree conor uh
and that's cool
you know you can you can find ways to
hybridize these things and make them
great together
but i'll point out all the ways that
they might not work
for you
the stimulation versus nourishment
argument yeah i
agree with that generally i just think
that uh
they also have the potential to to move
people in reverse as well like you're
saying with people inspired by
mir's edge and so on and whether they
would have got into parkour without that
i mean who knows maybe maybe not but
i think with augmented reality that
could be a new thing where
it can be outdoors as well versus like a
headset indoors
but yeah we'll see thanks yeah it's a
step in the right direction
yeah um it is a step in the right
direction
um but i don't know i have a thing about
authenticity
right i want to i want to be able to to
do
things in the world as it is
so there we go great
thank you ray for being here to answer
these questions
um yeah i really appreciate this i think
there's a lot of
there's a lot of rich comments and
um yeah for me it's
it's always exciting because any time
that i
explore ideas about movement and
play um the more curious i become about
what might be possible
so i'm really glad that rather than like
a sense of
completion i just feel more about like
an intrigue
about the possibilities so that was just
really exciting for me to have you here
desto a place and a community that's
become
important to me and um you've been
someone that's been influential and some
of that really
appreciated your work and admired you
for your work so thank you for being
here
thank you everyone for sharing this
space with us
thanks guys really appreciate it it's
really great to chat
and uh hopefully we'll do it again yeah
guys i'll plug an event for you um as
peter requested
we have with doug taran
a motive framework live emotional
processing
so some of you may be familiar with doug
i don't
know a whole lot so i won't say much
more other than that happens august 27th
at 2 15 p.m eastern
so check out that event and um
have a beautiful rest of your day ladies
guys
peace